I'm sorry.
对不起;
You...
你;
Don't be impulsive.
有话好好说 你别冲动;
As your girlfriend,
作为你女朋友;
I didn't notice anything wrong with you.
没有发现你不对劲;
I'm sorry.
是我不称职;
So I hope you...
所以我特别希望你;
No, no, no.
没有 没有 没有;
Calm down.
你冷静点 冷静点;
Take it easy. It doesn't matter.
有话好好说 没关系;
I'm worried about you.
我是真担心你;
Are you nervous?
你是不是也紧张了;
Yeah.
嗯;
Then why don't you tell me?
那你为什么不跟我说呀;
Because you said last night
因为你昨天晚上说;
you were afraid that
怕一有闪失;
all our previous efforts would be in vain.
之前的努力全都白费了;
So?
所以呢;
Therefore, when you are
所以在你六神无主的;
puzzled,
时候;
I should reassure you
我应该做你的定心丸;
and let you have no worries.
让你没有后顾之忧;
Not like now.
而不是像现在这个样子;
I make you worry.
让你担心;
I go to the library
我去图书馆;
because I want to adjust myself
也是想在你发现之前;
before you find out.
完成自我治疗;
Nan Bei, we're not only couple,
南北 我们不光是情侣;
but also comrades fighting together.
更是一起作战的战友;
So don't hide anything from me
所以你以后有什么事;
in the future.
别瞒着我;
Can you?
行吗;
We have been together for so long.
在一起那么久;
I never thought that
没想到你还;
you would be so gentle.
有那么一点点温柔;
Facing the finals,
面对决赛;
everyone will be under pressure.
每个人都会有压力的;
That's normal.
这很正常;
But I think,
但我觉得吧;
it's the same as the NCEE.
这跟高考是一样的;
The more you prepare,
准备得越充分呢;
the calmer your mind will be.
心里就会越有底;
So let's prepare
所以咱俩一起;
for the debate together.
好好备赛吧;
But I still have one
但我还有一个;
barrier in my heart.
过不去的坎;
What?
什么呀;
That's...
就是那个;
Nan Bei
南北;
Are you afraid of Liu Yanze?
你是不是有点怕彦泽呀;
Who's afraid of him?
谁怕他了;
Why are you trembling?
那你抖什么呀;
I am excited
我这是快要拿冠军了;
about winning the championship.
我激动的;
Nan Bei, it doesn't matter.
南北 没事的;
This is the psychological reaction.
你是心理反应;
I've been like this before.
我之前也这样;
Why don't you let Ma Nan help you?
要不让马楠给你治治;
You're having the pre-match stress response.
你这是赛前应激反应;
It's called being cowardly.
俗称;
How can you say that about him?
你们怎么能这么说他呢;
Help him figure it out.
帮他想想办法吧;
Or I ask Liu Yanze to be merciful.
要不我让彦泽手下留情;
Maybe you should see a therapist.
要不去看看心理医生吧;
Eat some croton and quit the debate with dignity.
吃点巴豆 体面退赛;
You...
你们;
Can you have a little human nature
同为队友 ;
as teammates?
能不能有点人性啊;
I'm going out to practice my song.
那个 我出去练练歌;
Me, too.
我 我也去;
What are you doing?
你干嘛去;
I want to listen to music.
我 我听听歌不行啊;
That's why I love you.
于是才能爱你呢;
They're training.
他们在训练;
Can you two stay here?
你们俩在这儿好吗;
I'm not going back.
我不回去;
They'll laugh at me.
回去也是被他们笑话;
They're caring about you.
他们也是关心你啊;
You also think it's not good for me
你也觉得现在大战在即;
to be like this now, right?
我这样不好吧;
I can understand your situation.
我特别理解你;
Really?
真的;
We have another band in our school.
咱们学校还有一支乐队;
Do you two know?
你们俩知道吗;
Yeah.
知道啊;
They seem to have performances every year.
好像每年都有演出;
Why don't you
为什么每年晚会上;
go to the party every year?
你们都没有去啊;
Because every school party
因为每年学校晚会;
only needs a band to perform.
都只需要一支乐队表演;
We lost to them
每次选拔;
in every selection.
我们都输给了他们;
I haven't won Yin Nan either.
我也没有赢过殷楠啊;
No.
没有啊;
You won her last time when you ate chili.
你上次吃辣椒就赢她了;
Don't mention it, okay?
这事就别说了行吗;
Actually, I know
其实我知道;
I have almost the same strength
我现在和刘彦泽的;
as Liu Yanze now.
实力差不多;
But I never
但是我好像从来没有;
have won him once
在一次辩论场上;
in a debate.
赢过他一次;
Every time I think I can
每次我觉得我可以;
win,
赢了的时候;
it ends in failure.
都以失败而告终;
It becomes a habit now.
现在已经养成习惯了;
I feel habitually
习惯性地觉得;
I'm going to lose to him this time.
这次我也会输给他;
It's scary.
挺可怕的;
Everybody's afraid to lose.
每一个人都怕输嘛;
It's normal.
这很正常的;
But you can think about it from another way.
不过换个角度想一想;
Maybe we are
也许咱们离;
one step away from victory.
胜利就差一步了;
I don't want to lose.
我不想输;
I don't want you to lose.
我也不想你输;
I have a habit.
我有个习惯;
When I'm unhappy, I'll sing.
一不开心就想唱歌;
Go ahead.
唱吧;
We have a new habit.
我俩也有个新习惯;
When we're unhappy, we want to hear others sing.
一不开心就想听人唱歌;
Do you believe in miracles?
你相信奇迹吗;
No.
不信;
How about you?
你呢;
Neither do I.
我也不信;
So I don't think this time
所以我觉得这次;
I can win Liu Yanze.
我不一定能赢刘彦泽;
It doesn't matter.
赢不了赢不了呗;
We can cry
大不了咱俩一起去;
on each other's shoulder.
抱头痛哭;
Will you think I
你会不会觉得我;
drop the ball at the last minute?
关键时刻掉链子;
Never.
从来都不会;
When I'm hesitant
当初在我犹豫;
to join the team two,
要不要进二队的时候;
you encourage me.
是你鼓励我;
When I have a conflict with Yin Nan,
我跟殷楠不对付的时候;
you also support me.
也是你支持我;
And several times
还有我好几次;
when I feel too tired
累到觉得自己;
to stick to it,
挺不过去的时候;
you are always with me.
也是你一直陪着我来着;
So in my heart,
所以在我心里面;
no matter what,
不论哪一方面;
let alone Liu Yanze,
别说刘彦泽了;
no one can compare to you.
谁也比不上你;
For you,
为了你;
for our team,
为了咱们队;
I will do my best.
我一定会全力以赴的;
Nan Bei
南北;
But I think
但是我觉得;
who works harder
谁更努力;
is more hopeful.
谁就更有希望;
This kind of thing
这种事情;
does not require miracles at all.
根本不需要奇迹;
Brothers, I completely collapse.
兄弟们 我彻底崩了;
For my educated and reasonable,
为了我知书达理;
gentle and lovely girlfriend, Xiaoyu,
温柔可人的女神小鱼;
you must help me
你们在这个时候;
at this time.
一定要帮帮我;
Educated and reasonable? Gentle and lovely ?
知书达理 温柔可人;
Who?
谁;
Come on.
去去去 ;
Go away.
一边拉子去吧你;
Help me.
帮帮我;
I enroll you in a stress relief class.
给你报了减压班;
Go early tomorrow morning.
明天一大早去吧;
Good brother.
好兄弟;
Breathe in.
吸气;
Breathe out.
呼气;
Touch your abdomen with your hands gently.
手轻轻摸摸你的腹部;
Touch your abdomen with your hands.
手摸摸你的腹部;
Feel
感受;
the power from your baby.
来自宝宝的力量;
When making an appointment,
预约的时候呀;
you hope that it works quickly.
你说要速成;
I prepare a few boxes of medicine for you.
我就给你准备了几盒药;
Modified Xiaoyao Pill
加味逍遥丸;
Ginseng Spleen-invigorating Bolus
人参归脾丸;
Liuwei Dihuang Pill
六味地黄丸;
Strengthening waist and kidney...
壮腰健肾;
Excuse me, this is mine.
不好意思这是我的;
Aren't you a western doctor?
您不是西医吗;
The combination of Chinese and Western medicine has a fast curative effect.
中西合并疗效快呀;
But these drugs are useless for kidney deficiency.
但这些药对肾亏没用啊;
This disease mainly
这病主要还是要;
depends on self-treatment.
靠自身医治;
Willing to hear the details.
愿闻其详;
Psychologically speaking,
从心理上讲;
this disease
这种病;
is actually a state of your mind.
其实就是你的一个心态;
Come on.
加油啊;
We all like your band very much.
我们都很喜欢你的乐队;
Thank you.
谢谢;
What are you drawing?
画什么呢;
You draw this.
这个是你画的;
This is spread rapidly on the campus network.
校内网传疯了这个;
That's right.
没错;
I'm the author.
作者的本尊就是我;
I heard about the band.
我听了乐队的事;
I think it's a pity.
觉得太可惜了;
So I draw a short comic
就画了个短片漫画;
and posted on the campus network.
发在校园网上;
I drew casually.
本来也就随便画画;
I didn't expect a good response.
谁想到就反响不错;
Their band has a lot of fans.
他们乐队粉丝蛮多的;
Moreover,
不止;
they also pull me
他们还把我;
to the fan base.
拉到他们粉丝群里;
Some people in the group
群里一直有人;
have been begging not to dissolve.
求不要让他们解散;
They want to hear them sing again.
还想再听他们唱一次;
And you see...
而且你看;
There are so many fans of yours
学校里面真的有超多;
in the school.
你们的粉丝的;
And they all support you very much.
而且都很支持你们;
There are still many people
还有很多人在;
who leave a message below
下面留言说;
and say they want to hear you sing again.
想再听你们唱一次呢;
That's right.
没错;
So many people in the school
原来学校有这么多人;
know us.
都知道我们呀;
Even I have a fan base. Look.
连我都有粉丝群呢 快看;
It's really well painted.
画得真好;
Thank you, Dango.
谢谢你啊 团子;
It's ok.
没事 没事;
This is mainly because your stories
主要还是你们的;
are inspirational.
故事励志嘛;
Look. There is
你看下面有一个置顶的;
a top post.
帖子;
Take a look, Shui.
水哥 你看一眼;
They also want you
他们还说想让你;
to participate in
去参加那个;
the selection
校毕业晚会的;
of the school graduation party.
节目选拔呢;
Hundreds of people
已经有好几百个人;
have already voted.
投票了;
We
到时候我们;
will go to be your
也去给你们当;
support groups.
粉丝后援团;
No problem.
没有问题;
What's the matter?
怎么了;
Oh my god.
天哪;
I didn't expect you to
没想到你们比;
be more miserable than us.
我们还惨啊;
Before, you may have always felt that
之前你们可能一直是;
you are isolated
觉得自己是孤立;
and helpless.
无援的状态;
Now so many people
现在这么多人;
are supporting you.
支持你们了;
What if it will work?
万一就能行呢;
Support can't change the result.
支持也改变不了结果;
Unless a miracle happens.
除非有奇迹发生;
Do you believe in miracles?
你们相信奇迹吗;
I don't believe it anyway.
反正我不信;
Come on.
走了;
Team 235
反方二三五辩论队;
becomes the champion of this provincial debate.
成为本届省大赛的冠军;
Congratulations!
恭喜;
Good morning.
早呀;
I haven't seen you all morning.
我一早上没见你;
I thought you ran away.
以为都跑路了;
What are you talking about?
你说什么呢;
How can Nan Bei do
我们家南北怎么可能做;
that kind of thing?
那种事情;
Then start preparing quickly.
那你赶快开始准备吧;
Time is running out.
没时间了;
Ah.
哎;
Don't worry.
放心吧;
My current treatment effect
我现在的治疗效果;
has reached
已经达到了;
an unprecedented state.
空前绝后的状态;
hello
喂;
The coach is gone.
教练不见了;
Then you go to
那你去隔壁;
the pork stomach and chicken restaurant to find him.
猪肚鸡店找找啊;
I'm not kidding you.
我没跟你开玩笑;
Listen to me.
你听我跟你说啊;
What?
什么;
What's the matter?
怎么了;
The old professor went missing.
老教授不见了;
Coach?
教练 ;
Excuse me.
我问一下;
Where is the patient
那个四零七的;
in room 407?
病人现在在哪儿;
I don't know.
不知道;
Dear coach, why are you here?
老教练 你怎么在这儿呢;
Coach,
教练 ;
call your wife
你赶紧给师母;
back.
回个电话吧;
She is worried about you.
她快担心死了;
Is it because of
是不是因为手术的事;
the operation?
又和师母闹别扭了;
When she was young,
她年轻的时候;
she liked a novel
喜欢一部小说;
called Notre-Dame de Paris.
叫《巴黎圣母院》;
She kept saying that
一直叨叨;
she would wait for a chance
说等有机会啊;
to go to Notre Dame de Paris.
能去趟巴黎圣母院;
How can we go abroad at that time?
那个时候哪能出国呀;
Later, we can go abroad.
后来行了;
I told her to wait for my retirement.
我就跟她说等我退休;
After I retired,
我退休之后啊;
I'll accompany you to Notre Dame de Paris.
我陪你去趟巴黎圣母院;
Now I'm sick.
生病了;
I have talked to the doctor about my illness.
我这个病我跟大夫谈过;
If I have an operation,
要是做手术;
there is only a 5% chance.
百分之五的几率;
I can't go finally.
就彻底去不了了;
If I don't have an operation, I can go.
要是不做手术能去;
But I can't sit. I have to Lie down.
但是不能坐着要躺着;
Buy a first-class cabin and lie down to Paris.
买个头等舱躺到巴黎;
In this way,
躺到巴黎;
she has to take care of me.
那还得她照顾我呀;
There is no chance.
没戏了;
Such a simple wish
就这么一个简单的愿望;
cannot be realized for decades.
几十年都实现不了;
It can't be realized.
实现不了;
It's not the end of hills and rivers.
还没到山穷水尽呢;
Coach
教练;
It's not too late to think about it now.
现在想也不晚呀;
I understand.
我明白 教练;
The simpler the thing, the harder it is to achieve.
越简单的事情越难;
Like you,
像是您;
you know exactly where the problem is.
明知道问题在哪儿;
But there is nothing to do.
却无能为力;
It is really helpless.
确实很无奈;
Xiwang
喜旺;
Yes.
是;
It's Xiwang.
是喜旺;
Xiwang
喜旺;
Look, it's wearing a red scarf.
你看它系着红围巾呢;
Xiwang is a swan.
喜旺是天鹅;
If I'm not mistaken,
如果我没有看错的话;
it's a...
那是一只;
Xiwang
喜旺;
Hey,
哟;
the state is back.
状态回来了;
I have successfully passed
我这叫已经成功度过了;
the self-denial stage.
自我否定的阶段;
My present level and realm
我现在的水平和境界;
has reached
已经达到了;
a different height.
不一样的高度;
Cool.
厉害了;
Tell me
跟我说一下;
what state you have reached.
到什么境界了;
Can you not be late?
能不能不迟到;
Take a champion and give me a chance to show.
拿个冠军给我长长脸啊;
Mr. Li, you are an adult.
老李 你都一把年纪了;
You believe him.
你相信他;
Too childish.
太幼稚了吧;
Don't kid me.
你少跟我贫啊;
I come to inform you that
我来通知你一下;
the time of oral defense has changed.
答辩时间改了;
It's changed to tomorrow afternoon.
改到明天下午了;
But
可是;
we have the final tomorrow.
明天我们决赛;
I know.
我知道;
But the school's decision
但是学校的决定啊;
cannot be changed
不能因为你一个人;
just because of you.
而改变;
You discuss it.
那你们商量一下;
There is no need to discuss.
不用商量了;
Ma Nan goes to the oral defense.
马楠去答辩;
Is your debate team all right?
你们辩论队没问题吧;
No problem.
没问题;
I'm here.
有我在呢;
It's the same whether there is Ma Nan or not.
有没有马楠都一样;
OK, don't be late and play well.
行 别迟到 好好打;
Don't embarrass me.
别给我丢脸;
OK.
好;
We will take the champion, Mr. Li.
一定给你长脸啊 李主任;
No problem.
没问题;
Come on.
加油;
At last it's my turn to say this.
终于轮到我说这句话了;
It's time to show
是时候展现;
our real strength.
真正的实力了;
I'm glad
我很欣慰;
I didn't train you in vain.
没有白白培养你们;
But can you
不过话说回来;
really do it?
你真的行吗;
Don't talk about us.
你少说我们了;
Are you ready for your defense?
自己答辩整明白了吗;
Well.
就是;
I am so young, lovely and energetic.
我这么青春可爱有活力;
In the eyes of the judges,
那评委看着;
I am better than you.
还不比你赏心悦目;
Although
你这次;
you won't play with us this time,
虽然不跟我们一起比赛;
we can still prepare for the game
但是比赛前的准备;
together.
我们还可以一起啊;
There is no difference.
没差;
OK.
好;
After I participate in the defense,
我参加完答辩;
I come to the awards ceremony
正好来颁奖典礼;
to win the prize together.
还能一块拿个奖;
OK.
行;
Then let's check the argument.
那我们就查查论点吧;
Check you.
查查你;
You are lazy in daily life.
看你平时这么懒;
Do you do your task?
到底有没有做功课啊;
It's amazing, Dango.
惊为天人啊 团子;
Really?
真的吗;
Do you usually
你平时是不是都;
hide your strength?
隐藏实力了;
Come on.
过了啊;
No. I'm serious.
不是真的 真的;
Look at this argument.
你们看这论点啊;
Wait a minute.
等一下;
This is not my handwriting.
这不是我的字迹;
Zishi
子时 ;
Let's stop here today.
今天我们就到这儿吧;
OK.
好啊;
By the way,
对了;
I recommended something in Douban to you
我上次给你;
last time.
推荐那个豆瓣;
Have you seen it?
你看了吗;
It's quite interesting.
挺有意思的;
Really?
真的;
Come on.
我跟你说;
In episode ten,
他们两个人到;
the two of them
第十集的时候;
were together.
就在一起了;
Then they will...
然后他们就会;
Zishi
子时 ;
We are in the library now.
咱们现在在图书馆呢;
Keep your voice down.
还是不要那么大声;
Oh.
哦;
I don't mean to blame you.
我不是说你的意思;
Don't be angry.
你不要生气啊;
You don't want to make me angry, right?
你不想让我生气啊;
No, I don't.
不想;
Then...
那;
If you coax me,
你哄我一下 ;
I won't be angry.
我就不生气了;
How to coax you?
我怎么哄你 ;
And then you won't be angry.
你才能不生气啊;
You give me a kiss.
你亲我一下;
Kiss me and I won't be angry.
亲我一下我就不生气了;
This is not suitable in the library.
这在图书馆 不太好吧;
Then I'll kiss you.
那我亲你一下;
Bye!
拜拜;
I'm sorry.
不好意思啊;
The...
那个;
The notebooks given by the organizing committee
组委会发的;
are too similar.
这笔记本太像了;
I took it by mistake.
我给拿错了;
Hello
喂;
Zishi
喂 子时;
I can't find my notebook.
我的笔记本找不到了;
I wonder
你看;
if you take it by mistake
是不是你在图书馆的;
in the library.
时候拿错了;
Yes.
是;
Then can you
那 你能不能;
give it to me?
帮我送过来一下;
OK.
好;
Pick questions that don't involve content.
挑能问的问;
Are there any arguments we don't expect?
有没有我们没想到的点;
Yes.
有;
Is it very tricky?
是很刁钻的点吗;
Can we handle it?
我们招架得住吗;
Not that easy.
难;
Then what should I do?
那怎么办呀;
Forget it. I'll
算了 我还是把;
give him the notebook.
笔记本还给他;
I'll go.
我去;
I was the only one who read
只有我一个人看过;
the contents.
上面的内容;
Do you want to tell him the truth?
那你要跟他说实话吗;
I will
有什么后果;
bear the consequences alone.
我一人承担;
Is Nan Bei all right?
南北 他没问题吧;
I believe him.
我相信他;
Have you seen it?
看了吗;
I-I didn't read.
我 我没看;
You don't believe me?
你干嘛不信啊;
I trust you.
信;
Don't you
你不是一人做事;
bear the consequences yourself?
一人当吗;
I despise myself.
我鄙视我自己;
In fact, we understand you.
其实我们都可以理解的;
But
只不过;
we know that Nan Bei
我们虽然知道南北;
saw it unintentionally.
是无心看到的;
The other side may not think so.
但对方不一定觉得;
Maybe they think
说不定还有可能觉得;
we have all seen it.
我们都看过了;
At that time,
到时候 ;
they may also complain that we cheat.
还有可能投诉我们作弊;
Nan Bei, you say
南北 你说你;
what a disaster you have caused.
闯了多大的祸;
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
对 对不起 对不起;
It was my fault.
怪我 怪我 怪我;
Even if I don't tell you
就算我不跟你们说;
the contents of the notebook,
笔记本上的内容;
I can't help thinking of
我现在脑子里;
all kinds of ways
也不自觉地想出来;
to deal with it.
各种应对方式;
So for the sake of fairness,
所以为了公平起见;
I won't play this debate.
这比赛我不打了;
No.
那不行;
You can't play this debate.
这场比赛你上不了;
I can't either.
我也上不了;
No one can replace you.
没法打了 没人了;
How about
要不 ;
our substitute, Gong?
咱们那个替补小宫;
He is an exchange student.
小宫他当交换生;
He went abroad last month.
上个月出国了;
What should we do?
那怎么办;
This is already the case.
事情已经这样了;
When it comes to the contents
但凡涉及到笔记本;
of the notebook,
上的内容;
I will not speak.
我不发言就是了;
Don't be under pressure.
你们也别有压力;
Prepare well what we should do.
该好好准备就好好准备;
I go out for a walk.
我出去走走;
Then let's continue.
那我们继续吧;
Here you are.
给;
Thank you.
谢谢;
Yanze,
彦泽 ;
what do you think of this argument?
你看这个论据怎么样;
Yanze
彦泽;
What's wrong with you?
你怎么了;
I'm tired after tidying up,
我刚刚整理累了;
so I take a rest.
休息了会儿;
Are you all right?
你没事吧;
I...
我;
It's okay. I'm bold.
没事 我胆儿大;
Do you need help?
你用帮忙吗;
No.
不用;
This is Xiwang's cage.
这是喜旺的笼子;
You left it with us before.
之前你放我们那儿了;
Give it back to you.
还给你;
Thank you.
谢谢;
Let's put it here.
先 先放这儿吧;
Can I write the story of you and Xiwang
我能把你和喜旺的故事;
into my song?
写进歌里吗;
OK.
可以啊;
Then in case this song becomes popular,
那万一这歌火了;
can you share the copyright fee with me?
能不能分我点版权费;
If it is really popular,
如果真的能火的话;
there is no problem.
当然没问题了;
What is the name of your song?
那你这歌叫什么呀;
Miracles.
奇迹;
Miracles, I like it.
奇迹 我喜欢;
What's wrong with you?
你怎么了;
Shui is leaving tomorrow.
水哥他明天就要走了;
Tomorrow?
明天就走;
Why is he in such a hurry?
这么着急干嘛呀;
Unfortunately, not everyone
可惜不是所有人;
can believe in miracles.
都能相信奇迹的;
Ah.
哎;
Do you want to come
那你要不要跟我一块;
to see Xiwang?
去看看喜旺;
I had an appointment with Xiaoyu by the lake.
我和小鱼约在湖边了;
OK.
好啊;
After all, it has been raised here
毕竟也在我们这儿;
for so long.
养了那么久了;
Let's go.
那走吧;
Xiaoyu
小鱼 ;
Thank Dango for helping me.
你帮我谢谢一下团子;
Her comics
她的漫画;
have attracted a lot of fans to us.
给我们加了不少粉丝;
Never mind.
小意思;
But didn't you go to the selection
不过你们没去;
for the graduation party?
毕业典礼的选拔吗;
Forget it. I'm a senior now,
算了 都大四了;
so I don't want to toss about it.
就不折腾了;
But
不过;
I plan to
我准备把这四年里;
organize the original songs
写的原创歌曲;
in the past four years into albums
整理成专辑;
and publish them on the Internet.
发布到网上;
It can be regarded as
也算是;
a gift for fans.
给粉丝的一个礼物吧;
After all,
毕竟像我们这样一支;
an obscure band like us
默默无闻的乐队;
is loved by so many people.
有那么多人喜欢;
It's like a miracle.
就像是奇迹一样;
It can also be regarded as
也算是给粉丝一个;
a result for fans.
交代了;
Yes.
是;
Come on.
是什么是;
There is a result for fans.
给粉丝是有个交代了;
What about yourselves?
那你们自己呢;
What are you excited about?
你激动个什么劲;
Because you're a senior,
就因为是大四了;
you should fight for
最后一次了;
the last time.
才得拼一下啊;
Besides,
再说了;
Xiwang and I
我和喜旺还指着;
are waiting for your song to be popular.
你们的歌火呢;
It is because we have lost for four years.
就是因为都输了四年了;
At last,
最后的时候;
I don't want to lose again
也不想再输一次;
and disappoint my fans.
让粉丝失望了;
Look at your
你看看你们自己;
lyrics.
写的歌词;
Even if you fall,
就算跌倒 ;
don't be afraid of ridicule. Keep running.
不怕嘲笑 继续奔跑;
Even if you worry, don't run away.
就算烦恼 不会逃跑 ;
Stick to it.
坚持到老;
Lost everything you still have pride.
失去了全部还有骄傲;
I have to find my own life.
我的人生我要自己去找;
Isn't this
这都不是你们自己;
written by you?
写的吗;
Aren't you a very upset
你们不是一支很丧的;
band?
乐队吗;
How can you write
怎么能写出这么;
such positive lyrics?
积极向上的歌词;
Anyway, you have become accustomed
反正你们也输得;
to losing.
习以为常了;
You will not be uncomfortable for a few days.
也难受不了几天;
But regrets will be remembered for a lifetime.
但是遗憾会记一辈子的;
You just said too much
你刚刚对小羊;
to Xiaoyang.
说得太重了;
I talked to Xiaoyang before.
我之前跟小羊聊过;
I know what she thinks.
我知道她怎么想;
If she loses
如果这次因为恐惧;
her last chance
她就失去最后的;
because of fear this time,
机会的话;
she must have regrets in the future.
以后她一定有遗憾的;
Just like our
就像咱们这次;
final this time.
最后的决赛;
If I don't attend,
如果我不上场;
I will definitely regret it, right?
我也一定会遗憾的对吗;
You have to decide this for yourself.
这个得你自己决定;
I will.
一定会;
Old coach,
老教练;
why are you here?
你怎么来了;
I am not at ease.
我不放心;
Take a look at the last debate.
来看一眼最后一场比赛;
Old coach,
老教练 ;
don't always talk about the last.
别老最后最后的;
It's unlucky.
多不吉利啊;
Let's go and talk about it.
走吧 去说说;
Definition, battlefield, offensive and defensive points, value,
定义 战场 攻防点 价值;
there are some problems in every part.
每个环节都有点问题;
We think
我们觉得;
it may be that
可能是对于辩题的;
there is no way to
讨论情境;
determine the discussion situation of the topic.
始终都没有办法确定;
So...
所以;
You find
你们觉得;
if you put it in life,
说得生活点;
it's difficult to explain the essence of the argument.
难以解释辩题的本质;
To be philosophical,
说得哲学点;
we have to do a lot of popular science work.
又要做大量的科普工作;
And the other side may not
而且对方还不一定;
be on the same channel
和你在同;
as you.
一个频道上交锋;
Yes.
对;
Because there are too many angles,
现在就是因为角度太多;
we don't know where to start.
不知道该从哪儿下手;
And we're more likely to win.
才可以赢面更大;
Each topic
每一个辩题啊;
has its value perspective.
都有其价值角度;
It's the core of this debate.
就是这个辩题的核;
The most important thing
一个辩手此时此刻;
for a debater at this moment
最要紧的是;
is to find the core of the debate,
找出这个辩题的核;
which is the value perspective.
就是那个价值角度;
Not
而不是;
the so-called methods that can win.
那些最能赢的所谓方法;
Then if the other side
那如果对方;
always finds the easiest perspective to win.
总找最容易赢的角度呢;
Then hit him.
那就抽他;
Then the opponent
那对方;
will win more games.
一定能赢得更多比赛;
But they give up
但是却放弃了;
creating more valuable debates,
缔造更有价值;
right?
的比赛 对吧;
Good.
聪明;
Coach,
教练呐 ;
your wife has been looking for you all day.
师母找了您一天了;
Why are you here?
您怎么在这儿呢;
Let's go. I'll send you back.
走吧 我送您回去;
It's time to go.
对 到这个点了 该走了;
Don't worry.
您也别着急;
I will broadcast it live to you
明天我给您;
tomorrow.
现场直播还不行吗;
OK.
好;
Well.
不是;
Remember.
记住了 ;
I can't spare anyone
明天谁把话说掉地上;
who doesn't speak well tomorrow.
我饶不了谁;
Old coach, your operation tomorrow...
老教练 您明天的手术;
Does your wife agree?
师母同意了;
Yes.
对啊;
I make the final decision.
我说了算;
Coach, coach.
教练 教练;
Sit down.
都坐下;
Prepare for your debate.
备战;
The right choice...
对的选择;
You're back.
回来了;
Why don't you tell me
你去学校;
when you go to school?
怎么也不跟我说一声啊;
They are about to participate in the debate.
他们马上要比赛了;
I am not at ease.
我不放心;
I go to take a look.
我去看一眼;
Don't have an operation.
手术啊 还是别做了;
I checked.
我查过了;
Many people
这种病;
will not
有很多人几年都;
get worse in a few years.
不会恶化的;
You have read this book for half your life.
这本书你翻了半辈子;
You know it thoroughly by heart.
都快要倒背如流了;
When I finish the operation,
等我做完手术;
I will accompany you to Notre Dame de Paris.
我陪你去巴黎圣母院;
Really.
真的;
It doesn't matter.
没关系;
We should believe in science, okay?
我们要相信科学 好吗;
Believe in science.
相信科学;
Today you guys are so lucky.
今天啊 真是便宜你们了;
You can eat as you like.
你们想吃就吃 ;
Drink as you like.
想喝就喝;
Enjoy yourselves.
随便作;
Because tomorrow
因为明天 ;
I'll not be here.
我就不在这儿了;
Shui, don't worry.
水哥 你放心;
I must have a good drink today.
我今天一定吐淹这儿;
I'll drink with you today.
我陪你喝点今天;
OK.
行;
Good luck in the debate.
祝你们比赛顺利;
I wish us all the best.
祝我们各自顺风;
Mountains are green forever.
青山不改;
Rivers are flowing continuously.
绿水长流;
We shall meet again someday.
后会有期;
Come on.
干;
There is one thing.
有个事;
Your fans
你们的粉丝;
write a petition of 100 people
在我们的漫画连载下面;
below our comic series.
写了一封百人请愿书;
They hope you can participate in
希望你们能够参加;
the selection of graduation party.
学校毕业晚会的选拔;
At the graduation party,
在毕业晚会上;
they want to see your performance again.
想再看一次你们的演出;
Really?
真的假的 我看;
It's true.
真的;
Shui,
水哥 ;
why don't we try again?
要不我们再试试吧;
Come on.
来 ;
The second glass.
第二杯;
Cheers.
干;
It's beautiful.
漂亮;
Yes.
是;
The next one.
再翻一张;
Look.
你看;
Ah...
哎哟呵;
I think we should travel by ourselves.
我觉得我们还是自由行;
I have studied Russian.
我学过俄语;
But we're going to France.
我们去的是法国;
Who can understand you when you speak Russian?
你说俄语谁能听得懂啊;
Oh, they don't understand Russian.
对 他们听不懂俄语;
Xiaoyang
小羊;
Xiaoyang, I'm sorry for you.
小羊 我对不起你呀;
Do you know?
你知道吗;
I was shocked
我第一次在迎新晚会上;
when I heard your voice at the orientation party for the first time.
听到你的声音我震惊了;
It was the voice
那简直是;
that an angel had kissed.
天使亲吻过的嗓子;
I was thinking about
我本来想着;
your voice, your look,
你的声音 你的样子;
and my music.
再加上我的音乐;
If we combine together,
咱俩组合在一起;
we will definitely make a difference.
肯定会小有一番作为的;
But I didn't expect that
可是没想到;
after our combination,
咱俩组合之后;
you didn't even
你连一次学校的;
get on the school stage once.
舞台都没有登上;
I dragged you down.
是我拖累你了;
Shui, I'm here.
水哥 我在这儿呢;
You have worked
要不是你这;
eighteen jobs in the past four years
四年打了十八份工;
to give me the opportunity to perform outside.
让我有机会在外面演出;
Otherwise,
现在也不会有;
there won't be these fans now.
这些粉丝的;
I am sorry for you.
是我对不起你;
If you form a band
如果你跟一只猫;
with a cat,
组成一支乐队;
it is much better than
那也比和我现在的情况;
with me now.
好得多得多;
Really.
真的;
I-I have a drink.
我 我喝一杯;
Shui
水哥 水哥 水哥;
Don't drink.
别喝了 别喝了;
You're drunk.
你喝醉了;
I'll send you home. Go.
我送你回去吧 走;
I-I have a drink.
自罚一杯;
Ah.
哎;
Let me send you.
我送你们吧;
It doesn't matter.
没事 没事;
You help them clean up.
你帮他们收拾一下啊;
My youth
我的青春啊;
is a pity.
太遗憾了;
It's just the little things in life.
你这才哪儿到哪儿啊;
Do you know what youth is?
知道什么就叫青春啊;
If you win happily, this is called youth.
痛痛快快地赢当然很青春了;
But after losing,
但是输了之后;
crying heartbreakingly is also called youth.
哭得撕心裂肺难道就不青春了吗;
Don't you have regrets?
你就没有遗憾吗;
I...
我呀;
Ah...
哎呀;
I have a girlfriend.
我有女朋友了;
The debate team also made a name for itself.
辩论队也打出名堂来了;
The only thing I lack
我唯一欠缺的呀;
is to win
就是在场上把;
Liu Yanze on the debate.
刘彦泽给打败;
You should understand me.
你应该懂的吧;
I know you do.
我就知道你懂;
On my shoes again.
又在鞋上啊;
Ah!
哎哟喂;
Dango
团子;
Help me send a statement
帮我在请愿书下面;
under the petition.
发一封申明;
I want to participate in the selection of the graduation party
我要以乐队的名义;
in the name of our band.
参加毕业晚会的选拔;
Count me in.
算我一个;
Xiaoyang
小羊 ;
I'm really glad that you can think so.
你能这么想真的太好了;
It doesn't matter whether we win or lose.
输赢都不重要;
This is the right decision.
这就是最对的决定;
Good.
好 ;
I like to meddle in this kind of business best.
我最喜欢管这种闲事了;
Leave it to me.
就交给我吧;
Do you encounter the principle of hypnosis?
怎么 遇到催眠原理了;
I don't want to think about Liu Yanze,
我越是不想想刘彦泽;
but he is always in my mind.
我越是满脑子都是他;
Don't worry about it.
你就别庸人自扰了;
Since you want to win him once,
既然想在学校赢他一次;
don't think so much.
就不要想这么多;
Just let go and win.
就放手去赢就好了;
Yes.
是;
No.
不是;
I really want to win him once.
我确实是想赢他一次;
But even if I attend the debate,
但我就算这么上场了;
I feel so sorry
我觉得这样;
for our team.
太对不起咱们队了;
And I think Liu Yanze
而且我觉得刘彦泽;
has known that.
已经知道了;
I don't know why he
我不知道他为什么;
doesn't expose me.
不揭穿我;
The debate competition starts at ten o'clock tomorrow.
辩论比赛明天十点开始;
My defense begins at 9:30.
答辩九点半开始;
Half an hour per person. I'm the third one.
每人半小时 我排第三;
OK.
嗯;
But I ask them to
不过我沟通过了;
let me be the first one.
把我排第一;
Then you can catch up with the game, right?
那你能赶上比赛了;
If I'm ten minutes late,
如果迟到十分钟;
it shall be deemed as an automatic waiver.
就视为自动弃权;
Although
虽然说;
the school is very close
学校离比赛的;
to the hotel of the debate,
酒店也很近;
it's only theoretically possible
但只是理论上存;
to catch up.
在赶得上的可能;
So I didn't tell you.
所以我没告诉你;
Wait for you to figure it out.
等着你自己想明白呢;
Ma Nan
马楠;
You are really a gentle man.
你真是一个温柔的男人;
Don't disgust me.
你别恶心我行不行;
I ask you.
我问你;
Have you thought it over yet?
你想好了吗;
Do you want to attend or not?
要不要上场;
I want.
想上;
But I think
但是我觉得;
I should make the right choice.
人得做对的选择;
Let's go.
走吧;
Don't be afraid.
不要害怕;
I am not afraid to have you with me.
有你陪着 我不怕;
This is our last time
这是我们最后一次;
to stand on the school stage.
站在学校的舞台上了;
For four years,
四年来 ;
we have been losing.
我们一路都在输;
I used to think
我曾经也以为;
I am a failure.
自己很失败;
But looking back on this road,
可是回头看这一路;
we gain more than
我们收获的;
we lose.
远比失去的多;
Although this time
虽然这一次;
we may still lose,
我们可能依旧会输;
I know
但我知道;
I make the right decision,
我做了对的决定;
a regretless decision.
无悔的决定;
Wait.
等等;
Then you go.
那你上吧;
OK.
好;
Change position.
换位置;
Interesting.
有点意思;
Please keep quiet.
请各位保持安静;
Our debate
我们的比赛;
is about to begin.
马上就要开始了;
Before the start of the debate,
在比赛开始前;
please set your mobile phone to vibrate
请将您的手机调成震动;
or mute state.
或静音状态;
In the course of the debate,
在比赛过程中;
please keep the arena
请您随时保持;
quiet at all times.
赛场的安静;
This is more conducive
这样更有利于;
to speakers' play.
选手的发挥;
Thank you for your cooperation.
谢谢您的合作;
Friends at the scene
现场及电视机前的;
and in front of the TV,
观众朋友们;
hello, everyone.
你们好;
Welcome to
欢迎来到本次;
the final scene of the provincial league.
省联赛的决赛现场;
This league is hosted by the Provincial Youth League Committee.
本次联赛由省团委主办;
It's organized by the college student association
全省高校;
of the whole province.
学生协会承办;
I am Wang Yini,
我是本场比赛的;
the chairman of this debate.
主席王旖旎;
It is an honor to host today's competition.
很荣幸主持今天的比赛;
Now, please allow me
下面请允许;
to introduce you
我为大家介绍;
today's judges and guests.
今天的评委及嘉宾;
They are
他们是;
Peng Feiyu,
东州社会科学院研究员;
researcher of Dongzhou Academy of Social Sciences,
彭飞宇先生;
Xia Weitong,
东州全省辩论;
founder of
联赛创始人;
Dongzhou Debate League,
夏惟桐先生;
Yu Xi,
东州交通大学;
professor of School of Philosophy,
哲学院教授;
Dongzhou Jiao Tong University,
于兮先生;
Zhang Hui, professor of the School of Arts,
福林学院文学院;
Fulin University,
教授张荟先生;
Wang Renjia, senior partner
东州创华律师事务所;
of Dongzhou Chuanghua Law Firm,
高级合伙人王任佳先生;
Liu Mingyuan, professor of Law School,
国经贸大学法学院教授;
China University of Economics and Business,
刘洺源先生;
Liu Xiran,
东州时代报业集团;
chief editor
总主编;
of Dongzhou Times Newspaper Group.
刘曦冉女士;
Next, I will introduce
接下来我将为大家介绍;
the debaters of both sides in today's competition.
今天比赛的双方辩手;
Why don't you tell me you are on?
你怎么没告诉我你上场;
I won't tell you.
就不告诉你;
At least it is a secret.
好歹也算个秘密武器;
Sitting on my left
坐在我左手边的;
is the negative side.
是今天的反方;
I won't show mercy this time.
这回可不手下留情了;
I'll try not to let you lose
只能尽量不让你输的;
too badly.
太惨;
Team 235
东州财经大学的;
of Dongzhou University of Finance and Economics.
二三五辩论队;
Today's resolution is whether the usefulness of the useless
今天的辩题是无用之用;
is useful or useless.
到底是有用还是无用呢;
I declare
下面我宣布;
the debate starts.
比赛正式开始;
In the first round,
第一轮;
the first speaker of both sides
双方一辩进行;
will make the speech.
第一轮申论陈述;
Let's welcome the first speaker of affirmative side.
下面有请正方一辩;
Please.
有请;
Thank you, Chairman.
谢谢主席;
Hello, everyone.
大家好;
The usefulness of the useless
无用之用;
is from Ways of the Human World of Zhuangzi.
语出庄子《人间世》篇;
It's about a big tree in the mountain.
讲的是山中一棵大树;
Because its wood
因为自身木质;
can't be made into any artifacts,
无法被做成任何器物;
it survives
反而在伐木者的;
under the axe of a logger.
斧头下生存下来;
Therefore, Zhuangzi said,
因此庄子说;
everyone knows useful,
人皆知有用之用;
but does not know the useless.
而莫之无用之用;
In fact, those things
其实那些我们平常;
that seem to be
看起来;
useless,
无用的事情;
as long as we change the angle,
只要换个角度;
we will find its precious value
就会像发现那棵;
just like finding the big tree
不成材的大树一样;
that is useless.
发现其宝贵的价值;
In today's fast-paced
在今天这样快节奏的;
era,
时代中;
each of us is trapped
我们每个人都被;
by utilitarian desires
功利欲望捆绑;
and overwhelmed by the cruelty of competition.
被竞争的残酷性压垮;
We are educated that time is limited.
我们被教育时间有限;
Striving is life.
奋斗就是生命;
We are asked
我们被要求;
to stay away from useless things
远离无用之物;
and not to lose our minds.
不要玩物丧志;
But is this really the fact?
可是事实真的是这样吗;
When I was young,
小时候;
I could not read
我不可以看与;
extracurricular books that were not related to study
学习无关的课外书;
because they could not add a point
因为它不能让我的;
to my exam paper.
考卷多加一分;
But it has increased my knowledge
但是它增长了我的见识;
and broadened my horizons.
开拓了我的视野;
When I went to university,
上了大学;
I couldn't join
我最好别参加;
various clubs
那么多七七八八的社团;
because they couldn't solve
它又不能解决我的;
my employment problem.
就业问题;
But it is the most precious memory
但它却是我有限青春中;
in my limited youth.
最宝贵的回忆;
Listening to music and watching art exhibitions
听音乐看画展;
can't make me earn a penny more.
它不能让我多挣一分钱;
But the pursuit of art
但是对于艺术;
and beauty
和美的追求;
makes my spirit happy and free.
让我的精神快乐且自由;
Therefore, my fellow debater,
所以对方辩友;
the useless is the usefulness from another point of view.
换个角度 无用 有用;
Thank you.
谢谢;
Are there a lot of loopholes
这个立论 ;
in this argument?
漏洞是不是有点多;
This is not loophole.
这哪里是什么漏洞啊;
This is their ambition.
这是他们野心大;
If we concentrate on this,
如果咱们打掉这一层;
there must be
后面肯定还有很多;
many strategies waiting for us.
战略纵深等着咱们呢;
If we don't speak,
要是不打的话;
we will definitely feel suffocated.
肯定就憋死了;
That's right.
没错;